Charles G. Shaw Papers
Charles G. Shaw Papers
1916-1964
Shaw, Charles Green, 1892-
4 linear ft.
Papers of the American author, illustrator, novelist, painter, poet. Correspondence (1916-1963); manuscript drafts of writings and poetry with original drawings by Shaw; exhibition catalogs; photographs; and scrapbooks of magazine articles and clippings compiled by Shaw of his and his friends' work (1921-1935). Incoming correspondence includes that of Josef Albers, Ruth Chatterton, George Gershwin, Sinclair Lewis, H.L. Mencken, George Jean Nathan, The New Yorker, Maxwell Perkins, Smart Set, Deems Taylor, and Monty Woolley.
149579
Biographical History
Charles Green Shaw (1892-1974) was an American writer, poet, illustrator, and abstract painter.
Born in New York City on May 1, 1892 to parents Charles and Eva (Morris), Shaw attended the Friends School and Berkely School, earned his Ph.D. at Yale in 1914, and did graduate work at Columbia in 1915. He served overseas in World War I.
Shaw began writing in 1919 and painting in 1932. He had numerous one-man shows of his art in the United States, England, and France and his work is represented in major galleries across the U.S. and Europe. Besides murals and paintings, Shaw created posters, magazine covers, and montages. Among other awards, he received the Nantucket Art Association Award (1958), Michael Strange Poetry Award (1954), and 1st prize in Nantucket Art Association (1960).
Shaw is the author of Heart in a Hurricane (1927), The Low Down (1928), and many other works, and he was a regular contributor to House and Garden, the New Yorker and other national publications.
Shaw also owned and assembled The C. G. Shaw Theatrical Print Collection, and was a member of various artistic and poetic societies including The Poetry Society (London) and the Institute of Arts and Letters. His published poems include "Into the Light" (1959) and contributions to periodicals and poetry magazines.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Charles G. Shaw Papers consist of correspondence, subject files, manuscripts and published versions of his writings, and scrapbooks.
Correspondence consists of incoming and a small amount of outgoing correspondence.
Subject files consist of announcements, bills, a certificate, photographs, receipts, and vouchers.
Manuscripts consist of bound and unbound drafts of books or articles by Shaw, often including his original drawings.
Published material includes books, exhibitions, newspaper clippings, poems, and published brochures.
Scrapbooks contain Shaw's collections of his magazine articles, press clippings of his work, and articles done by his friends and other writers.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged alphabetically (incoming) or chronologically (outgoing). Subject files are arranged alphabetically by topic. Manuscripts are subdivided into bound and unbound; unbound are arranged alphabetically by title but bound volumes are in no particular order. Published material is subdivided by type and arranged alphabetically by title; books have been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Scrapbooks are arranged chronologically based on the earliest dated item in each volume.
Related Material
has the papers of many other artists and illustrators, including fellow abstract expressionists
Grace Hartigan
and
Irving Lehman
. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Illustrators; Art -- Painters; Literature -- American Fiction; Literature -- American Poetry; Literature -- Children's; Albers, Josef.; Chatterton, Ruth, 1893-1961.; Gershwin, George, 1898-1937.; Lewis, Sinclair, 1885-1951.; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956.; Nathan, George Jean, 1882-1958.; Perkins, Maxwell E. (Maxwell Evarts), 1884-1947.; Shaw, Charles Green, 1892- Archives.; Taylor, Deems, 1885-1966.; Woolley, Monty, 1888-1963.; The New Yorker (periodical).; Smart set (periodical).; Abstract expressionism -- United States.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Authors, American.; Illustrators -- United States.; Novelists, American.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Poets, American.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Drawings (visual works); Exhibition catalogs.; Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Sketches.; Artists.; Authors.; Illustrators.; Novelists.; Painters.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Incoming
    - A (Box 1)
    - Albers, Joset (Box 1)
    - American Play Company (Box 1)
    - B (Box 1)
    - The Bookman, Burton Rascoe (Box 1)
    - C (Box 1)
    - Chatterton, Ruth (Box 1)
    - D-E (Box 1)
    - F (Box 1)
    - G (Box 1)
    - Gallatin (Box 1)
    - Gershwin, George (Box 1)
    - Guggenheim, S. R. (Box 1)
    - H (Box 1)
    - J-K-L (Box 1)
    - Lewis, Sinclair (Box 1)
    - M (Box 1)
    - McB., Henry (Box 1)
    - Mencken, H. L. (Box 1)
    - N (Box 1)
    - New Yorker Magazine (Box 1)
    - New Yorker Magazine, Harold W. Ross (Box 1)
    - New Yorker Magazine, James G. Thurber (Box 1)
    - P-R-S (Box 1)
    - Perkins, Maxwell (Box 1)
    - Smart Set (Box 1)
    - Smart Set, George Jean Nathan (Box 1)
    - T-Y (Box 1)
    - Taylor Deems (Box 1)
    - Vanity Fair (Box 1)
    - Wills Helen (Box 1)
    - Wooley, Monty (Box 1)
    - Unidentified (Box 1)
  - Outgoing
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Announcements for one-man shows (Box 1)
  - Certificate from American Mercury (Box 1)
  - Photos of Shaw (Box 1)
  - Photos of Shaw's paintings (Box 1)
  - Vouchers, receipts, bills (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - Unbound manuscripts
    - Guess Again (Box 2)
    - Heart Failure (Box 2)
    - It Wasn't Spilt Milk (Box 2)
    - Love's Lexicon (Box 2)
    - The Reason Why (Box 2)
    - Sketches, drawings, studies for paintings, etc, 1920's and 1930's (Box 2)
    - Sketches, miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - The Uncommon Man (Box 3)
    - What's the Date (Box 3)
  - Notebooks and bound manuscripts
    - List of bound manuscripts of Charles G. Shaw (Box 3)
    - The Adventures of Hally (Box 3)
    - Birthday Party (Box 3)
    - Heart in a Hurricane (Box 3)
    - Izzi (Box 3)
    - Jumble Pie (Box 3)
    - The Little Mouse (Box 3)
    - The Low-Down (Box 3)
    - The Marvelous Mirror (Box 3)
    - Me (Box 3)
    - Merry-go-round House (Box 3)
    - Most of Us Look Like Animals (Box 3)
    - Mother Booze's Nursery Rhymes (Box 3)
    - The Noo Book (Box 3)
    - No Such Animal (Box 3)
    - Red, Blue, and Yellow (Box 3)
    - Robin Detective (Box 3)
    - Robin Posts a Letter (Box 3)
    - Sunrise and Sunset (Box 3)
    - The Tale of a Kite (Box 3)
    - Train Ride (Box 3)
    - The Unplucked Rocking Chair (Box 3)
    - What in the World Was It? (Box 3)
    - What in the World Was It? [not the same book as preceding] (Box 3)
- Published Material
  - Books
    Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging
    The Apple that Jack Ate
    The Giant of Central Park
    The Blue Guess Book
    Heart in a Hurricane
    Image of Life
    Into the Light
    It Looked Like Spilt Milk
    Lady by Chance
    The Low-Down
    The Milk That Jack Drank
    New York-Oddly Enough
    Pitter Patter
    Toy Parade
    The Water That Jack Drank
    The Winter Noisy Book
  - Exhibitions (Box 4)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 4)
  - Poems
    - The Creative Review (magazine) (Box 4)
    - The Sphinx (magazine) (magazine) (Box 4)
    - Stem (magazine) (Box 4)
    - Wisconsin Poetry Magazine (Box 4)
  - Publishers brochures (Box 4)
- Scrapbooks
  - Miscellaneous clippings, December 1921-March 1929 (Box 4)
  - "Notes on Women", 1922-1928 (Box 5)
  - "American Institutions" from the "Smart Set", 1923 (Box 5)
  - From "Vanity Fair" and the "Smart Set", May 1924 (Box 5)
  - Press clippings on "Heart in a Hurricane", Mar 1927-Nov 1927 (Box 5)
  - Press clippings on "The Low-Down", Feb 1928-Feb. 1929 (Box 6)
  - Press clippings on "Night-Life", Sep-Dec 1931 (Box 6)
  - Press clippings on "Lady by Chance", March 1932-April 1933 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, January 1932-May 1935 (Box 6)